[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask Abhijit Show episode 157 I hope
you're all doing very well and uh before
we get into the questions let's see who
all is there on the live chat I can see
challenge accepted Explorer
charge 13x liger kuldeep
Shashank system tools
beneath
dong vikash kitten vinod patil Rahul
Mahajan
Dharmendra Dante uttam crude feminist
slayer costume
hello sir good to see you again
lots of parts
another part Giga Chad or something like
that system tools harmonica hero ketan
Karan Pikachu Amman
Explorer Shashank Melvin vikash shebeen
neat nikalna
Sanjay tanush ji Winnie Deb deep deep
vinod fatty just ate Indian citizen
shubham Napoleon Bonaparte is here bruh
I'm Consciousness
Joseph Stalin acharya Vault gaming
and lots and lots of other people
and everybody else thank you so much for
being on the right chat I really
appreciate it and thank you so much
um with that uh let's get into the
questions what questions do we have
where shall we begin with the questions
Let's uh start with this what do we have
all right okay and do
okay so this is about the German foreign
minister who came to India for the
foreign ministers meeting the G20
foreign
by India because she did not get a red
carpet welcome and uh that's the this is
the result of that this is just some
small sample of the comments that we got
srinu says that's not the reason for Red
Carpet issue the flight actually reached
before half an hour and this was
reported by the German Diplomat pratik
says German foreign minister did not get
a cold shoulder from India
she it was just her plane arrived ahead
of schedule and she couldn't agree to be
on the jet until
um senior uh dignitaries arrived to
welcome her please fact check Abhijit is
a mistake by your side though she don't
know saying the plane came early and
preparations were not made all that
Abhishek says wrong info about German
welcome your compromising facts for
Speed of video uploads it seems
Siddharth says you jump to a confusion
all those things okay so everyone over
here is saying that the the
uh our aircraft arrived early and that's
why the the preparations were not ready
and that's why the lady was given a you
know this lack of of red red carpet
welcome so
okay let's let's remove this first of
all so let's understand something the
Indian government is not run by children
the Indian government the government of
India is not run by 12 year olds
you can see what is the status of a
flight
let me show you how it's done I mean
what have we are we 12 years old all of
us
let's take a look at this open source
site called Flightradar24 you can track
the exact location of a plane the moment
it takes off
and when a very senior person is coming
to your nation when an extremely senior
Diplomat is coming the foreign minister
of a Nation you keep an eye on what's
Happening and where the plane is it is
impossible for the government of India
to miss the fact that the plane was
arriving 30 minutes early or 72 hours
earlier whatever
the Indian government is not run by 12
year olds
but maybe the comments some of them are
by 12 year rules I'm not sure
yeah
so this entire matter that was later the
clarification was later issued that the
flight came early do you know what it's
called
it's called a Face Saver
the German government put out a
statement that the plane reached 30
minutes or whatever minutes early and
that's why the arrangements were not
ready and the Indian government did not
dispute the statement by Germany this is
called a Face Saver
the Indian government allowed Germany to
issue a face saving statement but the
Indian government is not run by children
the Indian government knew exactly where
the plane was if it was coming early
they would have known about it hours in
advance
so these comments I mean
I I missed in the past I said that
Indians are less naive now Indians are
more mature in diplomacy in geopolitics
but clearly clearly I have to eat my
words because that is not the case
the Indian government gave a snub to
Germany
Germany has been you know playing
certain geopolitical games
and uh interfering in India's Internal
Affairs and making statements about
things that it has no business making
statements about
and as a result of that India has given
Germany a message
by snubbing their foreign minister but
not by not giving her the red carpet
welcome that he would typically give a
very high ranking official and then
Germany gave this statement to save face
and India did not dispute that
so the message was given Germany was
allowed to say face
so please understand that if an aircraft
is arriving 30 minutes early
and if it's a very high angle person
who's coming the Indian government will
know about this long in advance the
government is not run by children please
understand this please grow up a little
bit I would say
next
okay Aditya says what are your thoughts
on Modi Modi laosyan in China aniket
says talk about PM modi's Chinese
nickname atherva says please make a
video on Modi laoshiyan this term is
quite popular in China without says what
is the meaning of Modi Laos and why is
it becoming popular in China okay and
this is just a sample of the lots of
comments I've got about this matter so
uh let's take a look at what this entire
thing is about so this is apparently a
nickname that is that the Chinese or
netizens
use for Prime Minister Modi and let's
take a look at this so
uh this is an article on the Diplomat
how is India viewed in China and this is
where it all started the story as far as
I know it's by a Chinese person so let's
go down down and you will find the okay
in addition Indian Prime Minister
Narendra Modi has an unusual nickname on
the Chinese internet Modi laoshian
laoshian refers to an elderly Immortal
with some weird abilities the nickname
implies that Chinese significance think
Modi is different even more amazing than
other leaders they point to both his
dress and physical appearance seen as
lauch and like and some of his policies
that are different from India's previous
ones
in particular India led by Modi can
maintain a balance among major countries
in the world whether it's Russia the U.S
or Global South countries India can
enjoy friendly ties with all of them
which is very admirable to some Chinese
netizens so the word laoshiyan reflects
a complex sentiment of Chinese people
towards Modi combining combining
curiosity astonishment and perhaps a
dash of cynicism uh I've been doing
International media reports for nearly
20 years and it's rare for Chinese
netizens to give a nickname to a foreign
leader modi's nickname stands out above
all others clearly he has made an
impression on Chinese public opinion so
that's the deal about the Chinese
nickname for Prime Minister Modi Modi
Modi leashan it is a
it is a rather positive nickname they
have given they typically don't even
give nicknames to to leaders of other
countries but for Prime Minister Modi
they have given a nickname and a
positive nickname
um
an elderly Immortal with very strong
abilities that sort of thing and this is
uh Billy Billy which is something like a
Chinese version of YouTube or something
in which you can see there are lots and
lots of videos about Prime Minister Modi
and this is the automatic English
translation so the translation may not
be entirely accurate over here as you
can see we can change it back to Chinese
and there we go we try to change it to
English it will take time so they
clearly uh are very curious about Prime
Minister Modi and seem to hold him in
reasonably high regard
and this is another Chinese website
this is another automatic translation as
you can see uh laoshan seems to
translate into English as old fairy or
something like that or Mana boundless
um
so yeah it's it's an article that uh
talks about Prime Minister Modi in a
very positive way and it's it's clear
that they have a lot of admiration for
Prime Minister Modi so that's the deal
that's what this nickname is about first
of all the Chinese typically don't give
nicknames to foreign leaders and they
typically uh so historically they have
not had a very uh
positive view of India they have not
really uh admired any Indian leader so
this is the first lead Indian leader in
decades who has stood up for India who
has been totally
uncompromising when it comes to
promoting and serving India's national
interest he has turned India around from
where it was in 2014 and turned it into
the right direction India now means
business
Indian diplomacy actually has a spine
today
so all of these qualities is it's
something that everybody admires
if you have a leader like that even if
your enemy nation has a leader like that
you may not like the nation but you will
certainly respect the fact that this
leader is taking care of the country and
uh
so that's what the Chinese uh nickname
of Prime Minister Modi is about it's a
positive nickname they see him as an
elderly and very wise and very capable
person and the fact that they've given a
nickname speaks to the tells us that
they admire Prime Minister Modi you will
see such sentiments even among the
pakistanis the pakistanis have no love
for India we know that I mean most of
them yeah most of them have absolutely
no no love for India but they still kind
of feel a tinge of jealousy
towards India for the fact that India
has produced a leader like Prime
Minister Modi they wish they had
somebody like that
so yeah that's the deal with about this
this nickname that they have given that
the people of China have given to Prime
Minister Modi it's not the Chinese
government that has given this name this
nickname it's the people of China that
have come up with this nickname for
Prime Minister Modi Modi lioshan means
the Modi uh elderly Immortal or some
kind of you know person with
supernatural abilities elderly person
wise person and overall it's a very
positive nickname so it's it's nice to
see this interesting thing and you can
read more about that online
okay this is uh somebody from Armenia
who has written this it's not really a
question it is uh
a comment in historical Armenia before
the Armenian Genocide there were bosha
communities they were Indian originally
but Christians one of them is this
Armenian national
Hero's tatsi Murad let's take a look of
um that on
okay let's just Google it and it will
typically give you a Wikipedia thing
well okay let's take a look why not
statutory warning you can't trust
Wikipedia for uh information about India
anyhow this is about sebastati Murad
he was born in 1874 died in 1918 let's
see what it looked like he does look
Indian definitely it's an Indian
appearance yes correct
he was a well-known Armenian fidai means
freedom fighter or suicide women
somebody who puts his life on the line I
guess during the Armenian National
Liberation movement from the Ottoman
Empire he was born in whatever Village
and all that
um he he moved to Constantinople
he joined the Social Democrat hung
party and all that he assassinated in
Armenian former escape to Greece then to
Egypt it was a gorilla
and all that stuff yeah so it's not
surprising for me at least that there
are people in Armenia who have Indian
origin Indian ethnicity people who whose
ancestors came from India because see
Indians have lived throughout Central
Asia in deep Antiquity for for millennia
uh you still find ruined Hindu temples
in Central Asia Armenia is not entirely
Central Asia it's the Caucasus region
Arduino where the Caucasus region is in
case we don't know let us put the map on
the screen where's the map here's the
map one second so let's see where
Armenia is where the Caucasus region is
all right let's zoom into Armenia so if
you want to find the Caucasus region you
go west from India you get into the
Black Sea region there's the Caspian Sea
on the right the Black Sea on the left
in the region between these two Seas is
the cow Castle region
and there we have the nation of Armenia
and
you will find ruined Hindu temples in
this region in the Armenia in the
azerbaijani capital of Baku which is not
far from Armenia you even have a
functional Fire temple that was used by
Hindus as well as friends in in you know
a few centuries ago I'm sure it's still
operational today uh so the Central
Asian region has had an Indian past a
Hindu Buddhist past before Buddhism
existed it was a Hindu past
um
and Indian Traders they traded with this
region during the the turkic occupation
of India during the maratha era during
the British occupation of India and
before these the before the past
thousand years of of foreign occupation
of India
um you will find you will you will
see that uh Indian uh Hindu Idols have
been discovered deep in Russia as well
and to reach Russia from India you would
need to go through Central Asia and
maybe the Caucasus region so um lots of
trading communities used to live here
and eventually they simply assimilated
into the local populations that's what
typically would have happened so that's
why you have the bosha community in
Armenia and obviously they were of
Indian origin and eventually they would
have assimilated culturally and
religiously which means that they would
have adopted Christianity
and they became Armenians and they
fought for Armenia for freedom from the
Ottoman Empire so interesting piece of
History we have just discovered here
all right next Saif Mahmoud says I'm a
big fan of yours from Bangladesh thank
you sir appreciate it uh recently
there's been a much discussion
surrounding the topic of the dominance
of BlackRock Incorporated it is said
that BlackRock has a great amount of
influence on the global economy thanks
to its reach in the corporate industry
across the globe they have stakes in and
massive control over
almost so many corporations all over the
world it's also said that they control
the world is it true that they really
have this power do they have more
significant influence than anywhere
anyone else interesting question
BlackRock is a major corporation and one
that very few people somehow know about
because they don't really produce
anything it's an asset management
company
so they own stakes in in various other
companies they don't really produce
anything
their own Stakes shares in various
companies so if you look at the top 10
banks in the United States I think
BlackRock more or less has significant
Holdings in most of these Banks
the top 10 banks in the US so the entire
banking system in the US is essentially
in some way or the other owned by
BlackRock or BlackRock has significant
uh stakes in there if you look at the
major news outlets in the U.S Fox News
or CNN or whatever else it is most of
them have significant uh
well BlackRock has significant Holdings
in them interesting and not just the
United States it's it's all across
Europe even in Asia as well if you look
at the entertainment industry Hollywood
Etc Disney or or comcast or or Warner
Brothers or whatever I'm I'm pretty sure
BlackRock has significant Holdings in
there as well when it comes to Europe
the various media Outlets newspapers or
or digital platforms Etc
BlackRock has a significant uh interest
in there as well when it comes to social
media whether it's Twitter or Facebook
or Instagram or whatever else
BlackRock has a significant hold on that
as well
Australia also is deeply you know
there's a significant BlackRock presence
in Australia in Asia as well one one
years I'm not sure how deep it goes in
India I've not really had the time to
look into that but when one must be
aware of the fact that this is a
possibility
um
when it comes to the size the size of
blackrock's overall Holdings
it's I believe it's in excess of nine
trillion dollars
trillion not billion or million trillion
dollars
So when you say nine trillion dollars
do you understand the magnitude of that
India's annual GDP is three point
something trillion dollars
when you have Assets in excess of nine
trillion dollars
you are
you it's it's bigger than all the
economies of the world barring the US
and China
so that's how large
BlackRock is and its Holdings are
and since it controls significant
portions of social media well it can
influence social media
since it controls all these news outlets
across the world it can control the
messaging that's being given out
in the global media
and since well even companies like
Coca-Cola and Pepsi and whatnot it's
excuse me
much of them have uh
so BlackRock owns significant portions
of these companies as well excuse me
so yes they have massive influence they
have massive control control and
influence of different stories control
they definitely do have many
corporations
across the world
and because they don't produce anything
and because their logo isn't displayed
all over the place like you would see
other logos that's why very few people
know about the existence of BlackRock
but it's an incredibly large uh
organization nine trillion dollars plus
that's incredible that's humongous
that's larger than the GDP of India and
other nations apart from the US and
China so very powerful they can control
the messaging that comes out of the
media in the U.S
Democrats and some news outlets are
pro-republican and most are pro-democrat
well BlackRock has has Holdings in both
sides so they don't care
so they can put their message across out
there
um and so clearly it's it's a extremely
large and extremely powerful and
influential Corporation organization
whatever you want to call it
uh so yeah they are more powerful than
most governments yeah that's that's how
the world is run interesting
says I would like to ask something about
the mainstream Indian media why does the
Indian media not seem to understand and
reflect the real stand of India on
various geopolitical National
international issues it seems to always
portray the western side of the story
in order to succeed on various grounds
we must align internally on how we
reflect the Indian interest
our stand and direction to the world
could you please shed some light here
what are the different possibilities so
yeah if this is an interesting question
I've I've remarked about this in the
past the Indian media is clueless when
it comes to geopolitics they
um they essentially Echo the Western
um the the the the the the message of
the West and the perspective of the West
that's what is portrait in the Indian
media I mean I hardly watch news anymore
because it's a waste of time but one of
I remember a few months ago I was in a
hotel I just randomly switched on the TV
and I was watching some Hindi news
channel in which they were reporting the
the Western perspective that you know
Russia is you lose losing in Ukraine is
devastating Russia and all that stuff
well we know what the situation is right
now so you know
the Indian media simply so why is it
like this is the question and it's a
good question first of all see the
Indian media uh there is an amount of
there is a certain amount of laziness
there but let's just watch BBC or CNN
and then say the same things in Hindi so
it looks like we know everything so
they'll watch the BBC or the CNN or Fox
News or uh al-jazida or whatever it is
and then just regurgitate the same topic
talking points in in whatever language
in Hindi or whatever but then we have
the English language Indian media which
also uh repeats the the Western
perspective the Western talking points
why is that so one reason for this is
that they don't have any experts see
until until very recently the only
understanding of foreign policy in the
Indian media had was Pakistan
foreign international relations means
Pakistan Indian foreign policy means
Pakistan it was all pakistan-centric
so that's all they understood they
understand Pakistan reasonably well but
now the people have realized finally
that China is a bigger threat in India
is playing a bigger role in the global
geopolitical scenario the problem for
the Indian media is that they don't have
any experts
you're watching a new news channel or
whatever when the report about the stock
market they will bring in stock market
experts
when the report about the economy or
Finance they'll bring in financial
experts when they report about politics
they'll bring in political Affairs
experts who have spent their entire
career studying and understanding
politics
when it comes to geopolitics the earlier
used to bring in some people called
strategic Affairs experts now they these
these those people have been rebranded
as geopolitics experts but the problem
is that
there is no University in India or
college that teaches geopolitics
properly there are some courses on
international relations but they are all
I mean yeah nothing impressive about
that so there are no real
geopolitical experts in India academic
who have studied it properly from an
academic perspective and who understand
what geopolitics actually is it's all
about actually understanding history
understanding the history of politics
worldwide understanding world history
understanding the history of various
regions understanding how Warfare
happens understanding the nature of
power none of this is taught you have
various master's degrees in political
science or whatnot I don't know what
they teach in there but it's all
pointless and useless so the problem
with the Indian media is that they don't
know where to look for geopolitics
experts they typically would invite
various retired army Personnel generals
Etc but the the thing is that when most
Army Personnel see
see the relations between various
nations from a military perspective and
from the perspective of strategy and
tactics mainly tactics it's a tactical
perspective that they have so they will
look at the map and they will talk about
the the 100 meters here of the border
and this half kilometer there of the
Border that's not how you say
geopolitics
so that's the problem with the indium
Indian media is facing
and of course some some
news readers have become quite popular
because they have been covering
international relations for a long time
and uh but yeah the the reporting of
definitely uh leaves a lot to be desired
unfortunately so this is the problem so
then they take shortcuts and they simply
look at the what the Western media is
saying and they kind of repeat the same
talking points
um you will see that certain Indian
median media channels actually sent
their reporters some reporters to to
cover the Ukraine conflict but they
exclusively covered the conflict from
the Ukraine side of the of the fighting
none of them was embedded with the
Russian troops so that we can get a
two perspectives a balanced perspective
no they simply send their reporters to
the Ukraine side and they reported
everything from there and they reported
the great Ukrainian heroism and
patriotism and all the nonsense
well the Russians are also patriotic and
they're also fighting hard but they did
not report anything from that side so
it's it's one-sided coverage very clear
and very blatant
so then that raises the question of who
is funding these media Outlets where is
the money coming from and why are why
are they adopting this policy of of
showing a one-sided perspective of the
war why don't send three reporters on
one side and three reporters on the
other side and show both perspectives
that would actually
illuminate
things way better and give Indians the
viewers the correct perspective you know
both perspectives those what's happening
on both sides so
one possibility is that they are just
lazy they'll just watch the English news
of Western news and regurgitate the same
talking points in Indian languages when
it comes to the Indian media the first
of all there's the lack of experts there
are no real geopolitical experts in
India there are a few but uh I'm not
sure what's happening with them I know
of you that I I genuinely respect uh
but most of them are not seen these days
on Indian media and if they are seen
there they're talking about something
else so for the so there's a lack of
experts and then they they may then they
resort to inviting retired army
Personnel who have a very military
perspective I'm not I'm not trying to
denigrate any army Personnel or any
retired army officers I'm not saying
that all I'm saying is that they have a
very military perspective a strategy and
tactics perspective they may or may not
understand the historical aspect
properly geopolitics is all about
history some obviously will understand
it I'm not saying all of them are not
unlike that so these are the problems
and then obviously there's a question of
funding
where are these news outlets media
Outlets funded from where is the funding
coming from that is the biggest question
you have to always ask yourself
uh so yeah that these are the problems
that we are seeing in the Indian media
and uh and of course see there is I I
don't know of any
course University or college course in
India that teaches students what the
national interest is what is the
definition of the national interest it's
not some vague term that everybody talks
about and says that's not how it works
the national interest has to be studied
in detail what are the components of the
national interest and every nation has
different interests
so none of this is ever taught in the
Indian education system so then
everybody has their own weird
perspective of what what the national
interest should or should not be
um it's not about slogans it's about
something else so these are the reasons
why the Indian media
often if not always almost always
appears to be clueless and appears to be
regurgitating the Western perspective
these days we have a few few individuals
who are taking a different track but
yeah
all right
okay I got a bunch of questions about
this as well Watson says the US is
sending its ambassador to India after
two years of after a gap of two years to
New Delhi what are your views on this is
the U.S now seeing its natural and
geopolitical interests inclined with
India or shall we call it the Boeing
effect after Air India orders and
siddhan says could you tell us about the
new Ambassador selected for India by the
US government what are your thoughts on
him also in relation to earlier thing
you've said our elections in 2024 but it
has already begun for our Western
Partners well they are not really our
partners they are yeah so yes so we have
this happening right now
before we put that on the screen so uh
this person Eric Garcetti
let's put that on the screen
uh Eric Garcetti has been appointed or
is on the on the verge of being
appointed the U.S ambassador to India
after a gap of more than two years
roughly two years
they they are finally appointing uh an
ambassador to India and see even before
he reaches Delhi what is he saying human
rights to be the core of his engagement
what business does a foreign Nation have
talking about human rights in a
Sovereign Nation this is the problem
with the US they think they have the
right to interfere and meddle in the
internal affairs of of other nations
so even before this individual reaches
India
he is saying that he will have direct
engagement with groups fighting for
human rights in India first of all let's
understand that the U.S deep State the
Pentagon which actually rules the nation
has blocked the U.S president from uh
making a deposition or or putting a
certain uh perspective in front of the
international court of justice in The
Hague and accusing Russia of human
rights violations because that will
bounce back upon that is blow back on
the U.S which has committed much bigger
human rights violations in the past
Century or so anyone in recent times
so the big one of the biggest violators
of human rights in the whole entire
world is the United States and there
they will come here pricking human
rights to India
so
they have the yes they are on the verge
of appointing their ambassador to India
is it the Boeing effect it has nothing
to do with Boeing
do they think that national geopolitical
interests are aligned with India their
geopolitical interests are aligned with
nobody
when it comes to the US they their
geopolitical interests are their own and
they force other nations to align with
them
and their geopolitical interests serve
nobody else so it is not that their
National and geopolitical interest is
aligned with India inclined with India
whatever they would like to use India as
a counterweight and counterbalance to
China as long as that serves the purpose
and whenever it's done they will not
care anymore it is not the Bowing effect
because India has nowhere to go
there are only two Nations that Pro that
produce uh commercial high quality
commercial aircraft two companies one is
Boeing and one is Airbus so if India
says we will not buy your Boeing they'll
say don't buy your buy or boeings
wherever India go
so
so that's the deal so it's not either of
these things they're uh it's not the
Boeing effect uh it's it's the 2024
effect
the U.S would like
to see a weak government come to power
in 2024 so they would like to you know
interfere in India's Internal Affairs in
India's Democratic process in India's
electoral process
they would like to play this is what
they call sub-national diplomacy they
would like to uh rake up the issue of
this fictitious human rights violations
or whatever they would like to meddle in
India's Internal Affairs and now it
makes sense for them to send a chief
meddler to India
so that's why they they have appointed
this individual what's his name Eric
Garcetti so he's he's making it very
clear that his job is not to
um to be a diplomat and bring the two
Nations together and whatever an
ambassador actually supposed to do his
job is to talk about human rights it's
going to be the core of his engagement I
think India should reject him as an
ambassador if this is going to be the
attitude of the U.S
uh anyhow that's the deal so it's about
24. it's about 2024. they would like to
see a weak coalition government come to
power to India and they will I'm sure do
their best
to create trouble in India before the
elections in the build up to the
elections expect trouble expect more and
more U.S interference in India's
Internal Affairs over the next one year
until the next election general
elections happen and expect uh a lot of
propaganda on the western media and in
the Indian media as well including that
publication I just showed on the screen
all right
they just says why is it raining worms
in China why is China like this let's
take a look at this raining worm thing
let's go to Google and search for it I I
heard about this thing it's raining
worms in China
worm
rain let's take a look
oh my goodness take a look at this
so it's been raining worms in China
lovely beautiful and and apparently
these worms look like earthworms
so that's what the question is about why
is it raining worms in China why is
China like this uh
you know in the past there have been
incidents when it's rained fish
fish falling from the sky in rain
raining from the sky there have been
times when it's rained frogs in various
parts of the world so in various parts
of the world you have
rain of fish falling in the past you
have rain of frogs falling there have
been incidents in Japan reported about
falling fish and all that so let's
understand why this happens there is a
phenomenon called a water spout let me
put that on the screen
water spout
put that back on the screen so it's
essentially a tornado that occurs over
water a tornado is like a giant vacuum
cleaner it sucks things out it's in you
know the heart of the tornado is in is
it is a region of extremely low
atmospheric pressure so when you have
low pressure everything gets sucked into
it and it's a whirling tunnel so when
this sort of phenomenon happens over
water it sucks out it sucks up water and
sucks it sucks the water up into the
cloud and then the cloud moves on and
eventually it will disgorge the contents
that it's sucked up that the water spout
sucked up uh so when this water spout
happens like like it's called it's a
water spot it happens over water it's a
tornado over water so when this happens
over let's say a river or a pond or a
lake or the sea lots of fish will get
sucked up into it
and then eventually they will be they
will fall back to the ground to to earth
eventually because how long will this
stay up there uh so that's how you have
rain
of fish falling now if this happens over
a pond or a lake you may have a bunch of
frogs that get sucked up and then
eventually the frogs will fall down and
obviously perish unfortunately that's
how it goes
so you have a reign of frogs falling and
for some reason it looks like this
phenomenon apparently happened over a
place where you had lots of worms
so then it it led to a Rain of worms
falling and that that's as simple as it
is so that's why it rained worms in
China it's a phenomenon that is very
rare but it's known to happen it's been
reported and recorded lots and lots of
times and it's not a great mystery it's
just because this
process pulls up sucks out whatever it
is you know the contents of the water
body it occurred over
so if it happens over a place with where
there are lots of worms it's going to be
the worms that are sucked up and
eventually disgorged
somewhere else so that's why you had a
reign of worms in China very weird
phenomenon but it's not a big mystery
um
okay this is by prakar Gupta it's a
question from Twitter what I've used on
Mexico's willingness to join brics how
come a country right next to the U.S
border took such a bold step there is a
direct threat to U.S hegemony
well I suspect that democracy and
freedom and human rights will soon come
to Mexico
yeah
uh
see let's understand the history of the
U.S Mexico relationship
there was a time when Mexico the nation
of Mexico included California included
Texas included Arizona Colorado all of
this was taken out of Mexico
through Force
there was there was at least one war
between the U.S and Mexico and the
Americans
a next invaded conquered and annexed all
these territories
so
Mexico used to be much larger and it was
defeated by the US and the Americans
gobbled up on the territory all this
enormous territory and then you have a
straight line border between the U.S and
Mexico today so uh the Mexicans
obviously remember this they obviously
and and you know the Americans have this
policy of not allowing any external
interference in the Americas they are
supposed to be the only hegemen the only
great power in the Americas whether it's
North America or South America
and uh
they it's well known that they have
funded various extremist organizations
terrorist organizations drug dealers Etc
in Central America South America where
it is uh Mexico whether it is uh
Colombia
and and so on it's well known it's it's
par it's part of the historical record
the CIA and Etc they all whenever even
when it comes to Nicaragua Etc
they have interfered in the internal
affairs of all these nations and much of
the drug trade that happens is alleged
to possibly perhaps be overseen and
orchestrated by various uh elements
within the United United States uh
what do they call it the Deep State yes
so obviously these nations would like to
be free of of this hegemonic Overlord
so maybe Mexico is taking a risk and
maybe they have expressed their
willingness and their desire to join
brics obviously it is something that
will not please the US very much
uh so yeah it's it's a it's a risky
thing they are doing because they sit
right next to the U.S I'm sure you I
don't need to show the map where the
where the U.S Mexico border is but just
in case just in cases let me put that on
the screen and show the map
um Google Maps here we are let's go here
we go so as we can see the U.S Mexico
border has lots of straight lines
uh there was a time when Nevada
California
uh Arizona New Mexico New Mexico Texas
all of this I'm sure even Colorado if
I'm not mistaken was all part of Mexico
and the Americans took that by force
so um
so yes Nicaragua Guatemala Honduras
Costa Rica Panama Colombia Ecuador Peru
all these nations are under U.S hegemony
directly or indirectly mostly indirectly
uh
so I think it's a bold step is that it's
a dangerous step and uh I'm afraid that
human rights and democracy May soon
visit Mexico yeah
well I hope it one hopes it doesn't
happen but yeah it typically tends to
happen when you make such moves
okay
from 1933 to 1939 in just five or six
years how did Hitler
how was Hitler able to make to develop
such a humongous scary military how
strong was he when it came to leadership
so Hitler was first of all let me just
put this disclaimer into in case
somebody doesn't understand or realize
Hitler was an evil person it was a bad
guy he did horrible things okay let's
put that out of the way first of all now
how did he manage how did he succeed in
building up this enormous military in
just this this short span of about six
years so Hitler and his party the
National Socialist Party nothing's party
Nazi party they came to power in 1933 I
think and this ended more than a decade
you know of political instability and
economic disaster
and it it gave a clear direction of what
Germany's future should be like
according to the Nazi ideology so what
these guys did what Hitler and his
government did is that they instituted
very strict controls on wages and prices
and by doing that they ensure that
business remained profitable and they
sought to bring the inflation down they
also what they did was they took control
of all the labor unions in Germany so
this ensured that workers would not hold
the country hostage they would not uh
you know strikes and labor actions all
of this was prohibited so because of
this it ensured that businesses became
profitable and inflation went down then
the the Nazi regime promoted
self-sufficiency they encouraged or
rather insisted the Germans should buy
German made products and they cut down
on import they limited the importance of
these things so this helped boost the
domestic economy and domestic production
and it helped protect and promote
then
the
promoted and established a system of
otaki what is otaki it's a nation that
is not our key is a nation that that is
self-sufficient in all the raw materials
in all the basic things Russia is a good
good example they don't need to import
anything from anywhere they have
everything within their own territory so
the Germans tried to establish they
established a kind of otaki to create a
closed economy that was self-sufficient
and not dependent on Foreign imports and
independent from foreign influence they
also restructured the banking system the
nationalized many banks the centralized
the control like it is the way it is in
an Empire so this uh stabilized the
financial sector which was ruined by the
aftermath of World War One
and they also ensured that businesses
got the money that they required they
had a four-year plan or something which
was all about making Germany
self-sufficient in raw materials and to
reduce the country's uh dependence on
various exports and all that they also
established trade agreements with other
countries in Eastern Europe in the
Balkans to
boost their exports and boost the
economy and we obviously know what they
did to the Jews so they they
persecuted Jews they expelled Jews and
other minority people and confiscated
their properties and their businesses
seized their assets and use that to
finance the government's program so that
is also also there then the the Nazi
regime uh
it it uh
embarked upon a huge program of Public
Works the construction of dams of of
these big highways autobahns other
infrastructure projects so this created
jobs and stimulated the economy they
promoted industry they encouraged the
growth of industry and the major things
like steel production and weapons and
armaments so this modernized the economy
it it created huge numbers of new jobs
and by doing all this they were able to
First stabilize the economy and then
make the economy boom and because of
their emphasis on on the industry the
steel manufacturing the arms
manufacturing industry that's how they
were able to very rapidly build up a
very very sizable very powerful and very
modern military and they obviously uh
implemented a program of conscription
which means that German young German men
must serve in the Army so this obviously
gave them uh employment and it gave jobs
for the for the young men and it it
expanded the size of the military and
they also understood the the uh the
importance of of Science and Technology
research and development so they
invested heavily in research in
development They promoted scientists who
had bright ideas
uh and so much Innovation came out of
this so much Innovation uh whether it is
in in the first ballistic missiles were
developed by the Germans the first
cruise missiles were developed by the
Germans the first uh the first jet
engines were developed by Germans some
of the best aircraft designs came out of
Germany
uh military innovations military
strategy you know so all of this was
made possible by this entire
revolutionary restructuring of the
financial system of the of the economy
and all these measures that they took so
that is how in just five or six years
Hitler and his party were able to create
a an incredibly powerful military maybe
the most powerful military of all time
of of that time of that time so yeah
that is uh what Hitler did and obviously
he like we said he was a very evil
person he killed lots of uh innocent
people and eventually he dragged his
country into ruin
so yeah the the most important quality a
leader should have is that he must
succeed and Hitler failed and he ruined
his nation in the process and the result
is that Germany is still under U.S
occupation as of today
mother Chacha says what were the reason
reasons for behind the recent
re-establishment of ties between Saudi
Arabia and Iran who were the key players
though that brought about the two
Nations that brought the two Nations to
the negotiating table and what
concessions were made by each side
moving forward what does the future of
the relationship between Saudi Arabia
and Iran look like and what implications
could it have for the broader middle
east region
so let's understand what went wrong in
the Saudi Arabia Iran relationship
see first of all it's a religious
sectarian issue the Saudis are a Sunni
nation and uh
Iran is a sure Nation so it's a Shia
Sunni thing that the two don't get along
um
then um we also know that Saudi Arabia
has been under U.S sway U.S
it's essentially a U.S client state it's
been that way for the longest time and
after the Islamic revolution in Iran
Iran is seen by the us as one of its
primary enemies
and the Americans have imposed a very
harsh sanctions on Iran and tried to
totally ruin Iran's economy
and Saudi Arabia is on the side of the
U.S and Saudi Arabia also supported Iraq
during this uh during the iran-iraq war
so all of this historical baggage is
there this is which is why the two sides
don't uh trust each other and there's a
huge amount of hostility between the two
uh in the in the 1990s and early 2000s
there was a period of good relations
between Saudi Arabia and Iran they even
uh
came to certain agreements and all that
they signed some agreements of
cooperation friendship all that
uh
then what happened in recent times is I
believe in 2016 or something the Saudis
executed a dissident who was a Shia or
something like that and that is the
incident that prompted the Iran to break
off its relations with Saudi Arabia
there were protests in Iran and Saudi uh
embassies were stormed or something like
that
um and because of this this escalating
tension and hostilities the two Nations
broke off diplomatic ties this is in
2016.
um
now what we see is that uh there's a new
leader new ruler in Saudi Arabia uh
Prince Mohammed bin Salman he's the de
facto ruler of Saudi Arabia he is
focusing on modernizing and transforming
Saudi Arabia today you see that the US
is no longer dependent on Saudi Arabia
for oil the US is more or less
self-sufficient the US is now a net
exporter of oil and petroleum products
and uh so the Saudi Arabian regime
realizes that uh you cannot keep on
banking on oil forever
the only reason for the incredible
prosperity in Saudi Saudi Arabia is the
oil production so you can't keep banking
on that forever so Muhammad bin Salman
is trying to transform Saudi Arabia he
has made the nation a little more
liberal little more Progressive in the
real sense I mean women have been given
rights for a change they can now Drive
they can now keep their hair open show
their hair in public or something like
that yeah so there are reforms there uh
and the Muhammad bin Salman has this
this plan 20 30 or something by 2030 he
wants to totally transform Saudi Arabia
and make the economy more dependent on
on
tourism and other things
so uh there is a transformation that's
happening in Saudi Arabia and for the
nation to remain prosperous and and for
the long term in the long term they will
need to have peace in the region now in
now Iran and Saudi Arabia are embroiled
in proxy wars there's big proxy war
that's happening in Yemen that no one
talks about it's a horrific human rights
disaster that no one talks about uh the
houthis are supported by by Iran and the
opponents of the houthis are supported
by the Saudis and this proxy what is
going on and the two Nations Saudi
Arabia and Iran have Tangled in other
places as well like Syria and other
places
so there is this long-standing hostility
between the two Nations but Muhammad bil
Salman realizes that the nation the
region needs needs peace and stability
for his Nation to keep prospering the
Iranians are also they have been
suffering from U.S sanctions for a very
long time they would also like to see
some some stability and better relations
with the neighbors
uh and obviously the the U.S influence
not power U.S influence in the region is
decreasing its waning
um there is a reproshmo of sorts between
Saudi Arabia and Israel as well so all
there's a very complex scenario there so
it is in both Nations interest
to re-establish diplomatic relations and
to to tone down to some extent the
hostility the Yemen war will still go on
it's not that easy to end that war for
various reasons which I will not go into
right now because that's this is not the
topic uh so that's why this this
development has happened and the Chinese
have taken the initiative to bring the
two Nations together and have the
agreement or whatever it is signed in
Beijing and the official statement given
out by the Saudi foreign Ministry uh
recognizes the fact that China played a
role in this you know a significant role
in this so the diplomatic relations are
now reopened and both Nations will
reopen their embassies in both in the
respective uh Nation within the next two
months
and uh both Nations apparently want to
be part of brics as well so for that
also it makes sense to reopen
re-establish diplomatic relations so it
looks like uh so the Saudis would like
to kind of wean themselves off of U.S
influence the U.S has too much power in
the region
uh they would like to
Embrace a more multi-polar world
uh so these are the developments that's
happening so the food is the future of
the relationship I think the Yemen proxy
war will continue unfortunately it's
terrible for the people of Yemen but
that's what it is it's not that easy to
disengage from that even if Saudi Arabia
withdraws its support from one group but
it's it's a very complicated issue it's
an issue that goes back more than a
century and definitely since the 1970s
80s and 90s it's it's a proxy war that's
essentially been
this the war is happening between the
houthi rebels and the government the
government in Yemen is supported by the
Saudis the houthis are supported by Iran
now the Saudis got enrolled in this at
the base of the US actually if you go
back in history and study some history
so it's a very complicated scenario so
there's gonna be hostility there's gonna
be tensions but at least they are
talking now and they have diplomatic
ties and hopefully in the future they
may you know succeed eventually in the
long run to bring down the tensions and
establish more friendly relations uh so
in the broader Middle East Middle East
region you are seeing a shifting of
priorities uh
Every Nation realizes that you cannot
keep on depending on the U.S forever the
US influence is winning not power
influence is winning the Chinese are
trying to show that you know and the
Chinese are also making this play the
Chinese are trying to show the world
that the we have this diplomatic
influence and we can get two
eliminations together sit down together
and resolve the differences and they may
want to play the same role of a mediator
in the Ukraine conflict as well that may
be the big game they are playing so that
is the situation that is what's
happening right now uh the Middle East
is extremely complicated it's been
ruined and totally complicated
by the West
so we are a long way off from
from complete normalcy and and peace in
the Middle East
Danielle Nicholson says with the soon to
be a formed integrated rocket Force as
the fourth military arm of the Indian
Armed Forces is India now looking at the
contactless war strategy vis-a-vis China
how long would it take us to attain the
level at which the people's Liberation
Army rocket Force already are
interesting question
so yes India is about to form the what
what is going to be called the
integrated rocket force of the Indian
military it's going to be the fourth
fourth arm of the Indian military after
the Army Navy and the Air Force
so uh
so we have so India is more or less
self-sufficient when it comes to
missiles especially when it comes to
ballistic missiles
uh when it comes to cruise missiles we
are still perfecting the technology when
we have this subsonic missile what is it
called nearby is it so in which we we
are developing the the the motor
a turbo fan motor I think it's called
the money or something it's under
development and it could soon enter uh
production so once we have that the
indigenous the the
subsonic cruise missile will be 100
indigenous when it comes to ballistic
missiles India is 100 100 totally
indigenous when it comes to the
supersonic brahmos
it is significantly into indigenous but
the I think the guidance system and the
Ramjet motor is is imported from Russia
and these are the terms of the brahmos
corporation it's gonna be that way for
the foreseeable future that we will keep
on importing the Ramjet motor Ramjet
engine and the guidance system uh from
Russia but uh I think it's time that
India should develop its own Ramjet and
scramjet Rocket engines and maybe come
up with new missiles new Hypersonic
missiles supersonic missiles
uh but overall India is in a very good
position when it comes to missiles uh we
also have uh
so these days you know what kind of War
has War fighting has changed completely
historically what you would have is that
if there are two enemy Nations
adversarial Nations so let's let's put
something on the map and just take a
look at the India Tibet border because
that is an excellent example of what we
are talking about here
so let's put that on the screen
so we have a this lengthy India Tibet
border which stretches from Pradesh all
the way to uh ladakh and jamun Kashmir
so in the past historically when two
Nations had a shared border and there
were adversaries and they went to war it
was the war always started at the border
with the two forces facing each other
that's where the initial battle would
happen and then the war will go in One
Direction or the other and maybe move
into the territory of one nation or the
other that's how typically historically
wars were fought
today it's the other way round
we have seen how the Armenia Azerbaijan
conflict has gone we have seen how the
Ukraine conflict has gone
Wars are now no longer uh
it's like like Daniel says contactless
Wars so the first
salvos of the war will be
will be done by by long range long-range
systems typically by missiles so
the the first strikes will always be at
the command centers the ammunition they
pose at the at the uh Army and whatever
bases at the airports at places where
you have tanks and ammunition and and
troops and all that so it's gonna be
deep inside the enemy's territory that's
where the first salvos would be fired
and because nowadays Rockets I mean
missiles can can be quite accurate and
pimp and and hit targets with pinpoint
accuracy that's become more the case
so these days
it's the the first action is deep in the
enemies territory on both sides
territory and it's typically it's the
the two of two armies that face each
other along the border they will
typically be the last to engage each
other in combat so the entire order of
battle has been reversed essentially
that's how modern Wars will be fought
so when it comes to the Indian army we
have we have artillery which is guns
then we have Rockets not missiles but
Rockets which typically have a range of
about 90 kilometers at maximum and then
we have a missile systems short-range
ballistic missile systems like the
pralay for instance which have a range
of I don't know how much is it 200
kilometers 500 kilometers maybe 700
kilometers so you can Target uh the
enemies assets at various different
ranges using all this
so it makes sense to have an integrated
rocket force uh otherwise what will
happen is that various the armed for the
the Army will have its own doctrine of
how to use missiles the Air Force will
have its own doctrine of how to use
missiles the Navy will have its own
Doctrine and rubric of how to use
missiles but you want and and they may
not talk to each other as efficient as
you would want them to I mean we have
seen we have learned the lessons of the
kargil war and all you know when the
Army wanted air support their support
took like two weeks to come and that
sort of thing I mean I may be wrong what
the time duration was but you know there
are all these issues that that have
occurred in the past so what we would
like to have is a single integrated
rocket Force where all the decision
which is like all the decision making is
done within itself and as per the
situation we can use the rocket the
missiles wherever required so it makes a
lot of sense I mean the exact structure
of how it's going to be structured is
not yet known to us but it it needs to
happen soon and for that to happen we
need to have sufficient quantities of
missiles it's not enough to have 400
brahmos missiles lying around in the
country obviously they'll be deployed in
the right places but we need thousands
of missiles of various kinds and we also
need to have conventional ballistic
missiles we have the Strategic forces
whatever it's called which which take
takes care of our nuclear deterrent
which is nuclear tipped ballistic
missiles the Agni missiles and all that
we so the the integrated rocket rocket
force will be a conventional force not a
nuclear Armed Force as far as I can see
and there will have balanced technicians
of various ranges uh so you know when
you launch a ballistic missile it's
impossible for the recipient of this
package the the nation that you're
targeting it is impossible for them
to know whether it is a nuclear armed
missile or a conventionally armed
missile
so when somebody launches a ballistic
massage you don't know what Warhead it
carries
um that is one of the issues when it
comes to ballistic missiles but yeah
when you have two nuclear armed enemies
and neighbors you kind of don't worry
about that too much
uh
so we have the the prelay missile which
is similar to the iskandar Russian
iskandar missile short range ballistic
missile we have the nearby missile the
showroom inside we have a whole menu of
various kinds of missiles so it makes a
lot of sense to form an integrated
rocket force and give them sufficient
missiles to fight an extended War at
least a short duration of War you will
need at least a thousand missiles I
would say but one I would say ideally
India needs to have a stockpile of at
least 10 000 different missiles of
various various kinds
uh so yes India definitely is learning
the lessons of the various Wars that are
being fought in the 21st century uh it
makes sense for us to invest in an
integrated rocket force to be able to
fight a contactless war against China
and to
to make them understand that it's not
it's not in their best interests to
fight a a war with India so how long
will it take us to attain the level at
which the park which the Chinese rocket
force is at I think it will take at
least four to five years for India to
attain that uh level first of all we
have to create the integrated rocket
Force we have to structure it properly
and then we have to uh arm it with
sufficient numbers of missiles so I'm
sure we can crank out the missiles that
are reasonably rapid rate missiles are
much easier to manufacture than aircraft
aircraft are extremely complicated
machines missiles are much simpler so we
can crank out hundreds of missiles a
year maybe thousands of missiles per
year if you can
construct the facilities so it may take
four to five years for India to create
an effective deterrent that the Chinese
would signifi would really worry about
all right next question
says
can you tell us about the invasion of
the kievan Rus by the Mongolian Empire
and why
it doesn't have an influence over modern
day Ukraine which is in Central Asia and
the Caucasus region interesting question
the invasion of the cave and Bruce by
the Mongolian Empire
yeah that's that's an event in history
that is not really
spoken about a lot let's take a look at
the geography
so
so about a thousand years ago we had the
kievan ruse which is the Slavic peoples
who were ruled over by a bunch of
Vikings the ruse and that's how the the
nation eventually got its name the
nation of Russia
uh so their Capital originally used to
be Kiev the capital of the ruse people
was Kev right now it's the capital of
Ukraine so at that time it was Kev and
they were called the kievan rules now
this invasion of the cave and Rose by
the Mongolian Empire happened in the
13th century after the death of the
great tringis Khan so chingis Khan did
not ever fight a war without just causes
he did not just randomly conquer a
country because it was it was you know
rich and he wanted the wealth he fought
for genuine reasons and just causes but
after his death his descendants started
fighting Wars for the sake of conquering
for the sake of Conquest so they would
fight unprovoked Wars so after chingis
Khan died I think in 1227 his son Khan
became the great Khan of the Mongols the
Great khagan
and he inherited his father's great
General subotai
bahadir the Valiant one of possibly the
greatest military General in the in the
whole of History
so uh
so uh this guy the the new Mongol Khan
the son of Genghis Khan he instructed
his General subotai to mount an invasion
of Europe
so I think it was in 12 37 or so that
subotai went with his army and he one of
the the official leader of the Mongol
invasion was I think Batu Khan the son
of jochi who was the son of chingas so
Batu happened to be Ching's Khan's
grandson he was the official leader of
the Mongolian Army but the real leader
was subotai
so they invaded the Russia
which was then uh the capital was in
cave and I think within a couple of
years they were able to conquer it very
easily I mean it was not that easy as a
make it sound there were battles and
sometimes it was quite difficult and
sometimes the Mongols may even have lost
a battle or two but overall because of
the incredible unparalleled Brilliance
of subotai they were able to make
reasonably short work of the ruse and
they were able to take care of another
cities and they allowed the Russian
princes or or the ruling class to keep
on ruling but they made them their
vasals they extracted heavy tribute from
them
uh so that was the invasion of the cave
and Rose by the Mongolian Empire and
eventually this gave rise to what is
called the Golden horde which was the
the Mongols who ruled Central Asia
eventually they became turkey fight
eventually the golden horde so uh so the
invasion of the Cayman rules were the
Mongolian Empire happened in the middle
of the 13th century
and it was pretty harsh pretty brutal
um and and the Mongols ruled Russia for
at least a couple of centuries uh the
Russians were able to throw off what
they call the Mongol yolk by the 15th
century or so with the rise of Moscow as
the new center of power
so that is in brief about the invasion
of ruse by the Mongolian Empire why
doesn't it have it have an influence
over modern day Ukraine as it has in
Central Asia and the Caucasus region
because uh
um
when it comes Central Asian Caucasus
these regions became uh islamized turkey
fight the Mongols of the golden horde
eventually themselves became turkeyfied
and by by the process because of the
process of turkey vacation they
eventually adopted Islam Mongolia has
never been Islamic I'm talking about the
nation of Mongolia over here this nation
has never been a Muslim Nation but the
Mongols who conquered Central Asia
eventually became turkey fight turkey
sized and they became Muslims because of
that
uh Central Asia and the Caucasus region
is is an Islamic region is a Muslim
region most people in Central Asia and
the Caucasus region I'm not talking
about Georgia but on or Armenia I'm
talking about Azerbaijan
chechnya all those regions which are
currently part of Russia
uh so because of that Central Asia and
the Caucasus became uh islamized in
Turkey sized turkey five whatever we
call it but Ukraine never
this never happened there because the
Russians were eventually able to uh
free themselves of the Mongols and expel
Mongols from Russian territory
so because of that it never happened
there of course there is still a
significant Mongol influence in in
Russia
I mean the the Mongol occupation of
Russia did do some good to Russia they
gave them an administrative system which
was continued to some extent even after
Russia became free and Moscow emerged as
the center of power and many Russians
would have some Mongol ethnicities of
Mongol ancestry as a result of what a
couple of centuries of Mongol occupation
and some intermingling of people and all
that so that's the legacy of the Mongol
occupation of Russia
uh
and that's why it doesn't it did not
have that much of an influence on
Ukraine
abhimanyu says is it true that the
Earth's axis was straight before the
youngest younger dryas event and it
tilted after this
uh good question let us take a look at
the Earth's axis so you can see Earth in
space it spins like this it rotates yes
and
it it uh orbits the Sun
the orbit is not a circle it's an
ellipse it's like a squashed Circle so
the earth goes around the Sun in an
elliptical orbit and all the planets go
around the Sun in similar elliptical
orbits
and the all the planets they go around
the Sun in the plane of the solar system
the plane of the solar system now when
when we take a look at the plane of the
solar system you will find that the
Earth's
axis of rotation is not straight it is
inclined somewhat
uh to the Earth's axis of rotation it's
rotating like this and it's going around
the Sun so the axis of rotation compared
to the plane of the solar system is not
straight it's inclined and there is a
precession also it's called the
precession of the equivalent of the
equinoxes
so the question is was the Earth's axis
of rotation straight at 90 degrees to
the plane of the solar system before the
youngest driest event and did it tilt
after This calamity so the younger dress
event is something that happened about
11 or so thousand years before today
it was a sudden period of global cooling
and they we have
discovered evidence of an asteroid or
Comet or or space Rock strike
a hidden a buried crater has been
discovered in Greenland a crater which
is an impact crater
and other evidence may also exist often
asteroids strike around this time so
maybe it was an asteroid strike that
contributed to the sudden cooling event
so that's called the global dryas uh
Theory
maybe that's why it happened
so the question is was this
space rock or asteroid impact on Earth
the event that caused the tilt of the of
the of the Earth
of the axis of rotation of the earth
well it's not the case
uh
the young address event if it was caused
by an impact from a space Rock was not
that significant it did not cause a
global
Extinction event which means it was a
small impact 66 million years ago there
was an enormous impact the chip impact
event let me show you where it where it
happened it happened in Mexico in the
Yucatan Peninsula where is Yucatan here
it is this is Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula
south of the Gulf of Mexico let's find
the child the town of chick where is it
Merida
and I'm where is it one second should be
somewhere here
this definitely is Yucatan
okay it's somewhere here I'm
temporarily unable to locate it let's
just search for it
and it'll zoom in there we go here it is
so this is approximately where the
impact happened now this was a massive
massive impact it was much larger than
anything that happened during the
younger dryas event
the impact crater itself is about 180
kilometers in diameter enormous half of
it is under the ocean under the under
the sea in the Gulf of Mexico
this was a major impact event and the
the object the space rock that hit the
earth was about 10 kilometers in
diameter enormous
like like a small City like a big city
actually 10 kilometers in diameter so
that's a massive impact so the younger
dryas event was very small compared to
that so it's clear that the younger
dress even did not uh cause the
they tilt in the axis of Earth's
rotation
I am sure pretty sure it was not even
the excuse me I'm pretty sure it was not
even the chip impact that caused the
axis of rotation of the earth to tilt
it would take something much much larger
to tilt the axis of rotation of the
Earth
so maybe this event was was the event
that caused the creation of the Moon
itself
so this is this hypothesis that Earth
the young Earth was hit by a small
planet which no longer exists it was a
major Collision
and this Collision was so massive that
huge amounts of lava and in the magma
and all that was thrown out into the
into Earth's orbit it eventually
coalesced together and formed the Moon
so an event an impact of that size
between Earth and in and a small planet
that would be something that would cause
the Earth's axis of rotation to tilt not
some small tiny Space Rock 10 kilometers
or so that's not big enough to cause
such an event so most likely it was much
older impact in the early days young
days of the solar system that caused the
Earth's axis of rotation to tilt with
respect to the plane of the solar system
okay swapnil says how does blood work
against gravity in the sense that it
reaches our brain from our heart a good
question so
we feel the force of gravity which is
because of the mass of the Earth so
everything falls down it falls towards
the direction of the center of the
planet
so how does blood work against gravity
how does it reach our brain from the
heart or wherever it is how does the
blood reach my fingertips and all that
how does it happen
so understand this uh let's say you take
a piece of glass and you rub it with
with silk or whatever it's gonna get
charged yes and if you have a piece of
paper lying on a table and you bring
this piece of glass to the charged piece
of glass towards the the piece of paper
it's gonna pull up the piece of paper
and so the paper will stick to the glass
so this small electric charge is able to
defeat the entire gravitational strength
pull of the entire planet
if you have a small magnet
small magnet and you have a pin metallic
pin iron pin on your table this tiny
magnet you bring it towards the pin the
pin will be pulled up and it will stick
to the magnet so this tiny little magnet
is able to defeat the gravitational pull
of an entire planet what does this tell
us
it tells us that gravitation the force
of gravity is the weakest Force we know
of it's incredibly weak a tiny little
magnet can defeat an entire planet
right so understand that gravity isn't
that it's incredibly weak let me tell
you exactly how weak it is
you we don't see them but there is
something called a neutrino a neutrino
is a kind of elementary particle and uh
the sun gives off neutrinos so trillions
of solar neutrinos which are given out
by the sun they pass through the Earth
every second they pass through us every
second right now there's a whole Flux Of
neutrinos passing through me and I have
no idea we don't see them we don't feel
them
neutrinos these Elementary particles
they interact through the weak Force the
weak nuclear force and this force is
incredibly weak
yeah but the truth is that gravity is
even weaker than the weak nuclear force
gravity is a million trillion trillion
trillion times weaker than the neutrinos
weak Force
so such a force such a weak Force it's
so easy to defeat it a tiny magnet can
defeat the fort the gravity of an entire
planet so how does blood defeat gravity
and work against gravity because the
heart pumps it and the heart is stronger
than the gravitational pull of the
planet so the heart keeps pumping the
blood of whatever times per per minute I
think depending on Person to Person
between 45 and 70 80 90 times per minute
so it's the action of the heart
's pumping that pushes the blood
throughout the body and wherever it is
supposed to reach it's that easy to
defeat the force of gravity of an entire
planet incredible
says what was the original name of the
Hindu Kush mountains the original name
of the Hindu question mountains was the
upari Sheena mountains
it's Sanskrit obviously
um
means um
the word Shaina in Sanskrit means eagle
so these mountains were so tall so high
that even eagles could not fly above
them that's what it actually means so
so that's what the original name was now
it's called the Hindu Kush the killer of
Hindus and there's a horrible
blood bloody story behind that and I'm
sure we all know what the story is after
the invasion occupation of India by the
Turks millions of Indians mainly women
and children were taken away as slaves
and they were made to pass through these
mountains these frigid mountains Indians
they lived in the Indian subcontinent
they were used to warm weather and lots
of them died in those snowy passes of
the mountains I'm sure if you go and
do some archaeological work there you
may find frozen bodies of Indians who
died there
and those who survived were taken to
Central Asia and sold off in the bazaars
of Bukhara and Samarkand as slaves
and you will see even today lots of
Central Asian people who have some
Indian appearance and you will see lots
of Indian looking people in Arabia as
well in Yemen and all that
so that's why the name changed from
to the killer of Hindus hindukush the
original name was the Sanskrit name
operation in the mountains
gaurav says what what do I think about
there being a stagnation in the field of
theoretical physics since the standard
model came out what do you expect where
do you expect the next significant
breakthrough to be
so yes it is true that physics
theoretical physics has hit a brick wall
the last great major breakthrough was in
1980 or 81 which was The Proposal of
cosmic inflation for which we have found
experimental evidence Cosmic inflation
uh after that there has been no new
breakthrough in theoretical physics none
whatsoever why is it so it's because of
group think
it's because a certain Mafia has taken
over theoretical physics
especially in the West
the string theory Mafia string theory is
a failed Theory it has produced no
experimentally testable predictions it
has made no predictions that can be
experimentally tested it's all math math
and you will see dozens of papers
research papers coming out every week in
Spring Theory but it doesn't Advance the
field of physics or our understanding of
the universe even one inch
so because all the funding is being
poured into theoretic into string theory
and and all that that's why
there is no space for research in other
in in other avenues
it's all group thing everybody is made
to think the same everybody needs to do
their PHD in theoretical physics if you
want to be a professor a tenure track
Professor you need to be in in string
theory in string theory I didn't mean
string theory
so string theory has taken over the
academic system the physics theoretical
physics uh
Academia in the west and it's producing
no results whatsoever so there are lots
of brilliant physicists young physicists
older physicists but they are all doing
the same thing
so that's why no results are coming out
and there has been no progress in
theoretical physics since the 1980s
since the early 1980s
there must be you know when quantum
mechanics was first discovered you had
people who thought differently
Einstein thought very differently from
everybody else today that is discouraged
today that is strongly discouraged you
you do research in a very different
in a different way your paper will not
get published it will not be approved
for publication
so that's the kind of thing that's
happening
uh and that's why there is this
stagnation so where do I expect the next
significant breakthrough there are so
many open problems in physics we
understand next to nothing of the
universe 95 of the universe is invisible
it's dark to us
70 is dark energy 25 is dark matter we
have no idea what these things are
various theories and models have been
proposed but none of them has been
experimentally verified or falsified
thus far
so 95 of the universe is not understood
at all zero
so that's a huge unsolved problem in
theoretical physics Dark Matter Dark
Energy what about the baryon asymmetry
the matter antimatter asymmetry I mean
according to physics theories and models
when the universe was formed 13.8
billion years ago
billion years ago in the Big Bang there
should have been equal amounts of matter
and antimatter produced but clearly
there was slightly more matter produced
than antimatter
what is matter and antimatter what are
these things these are different kinds
of particles which have opposite
properties such as electric charge when
they come together they annihilate each
other and produce Pure Energy so why do
we have more matter than antimatter
they still don't have the answer so
that's a big big breakthrough we need to
come up with what are black holes what
is inside a black hole why do we have
singularities clearly something is wrong
there that needs to be solved quantum
gravity we we don't understand gravity
at all
general relativity does not is not
compatible with quantum physics with
quantum mechanics in quantum mechanics
space is smooth and time is absolute in
general relativity space is curved and
time is relative the completely
different
ways of looking at the world so these
two don't match but we need to make them
match to come up with a quantum theory
of gravity so that we understand how the
how gravity is relevant in the ultra
microscopic Quantum world that's another
big outstanding problem in physics there
are so many more what about all these
free constants lying around in the
standard model of the the mass of the
the masses of the quarks
how I mean what is the explanation of
why a certain Quark has a certain Mass
why does the electron have a certain
Mass why do various uh subatomic
particles elementary particle have
specific masses we have no idea why
these are called these free constants
we have no idea why these masses are the
way they are so we have no theory of
that so once again that's a huge open
question a huge open problem in physics
then a grand unified theory we would
like to understand how the various
forces of nature are related we need to
unify them into a single framework
what are the four forces the
gravitational force the strong nuclear
force the weak nuclear force and the
electromagnetic force
uh so how do we unify how do we
understand all these forces in a single
frame as part of a single framework when
the Big Bang happened all the forces
were unified into a single Force the
grand unified Force so we have no idea
about that as well so that's something
people have been the best physicists in
the world have been working on for close
to a century and we have made no
breakthrit so these are some of the
problems the open problems in physics
there are many more
so uh the ultimate fate of the universe
we know that the Universe began 13.8
roughly billion years ago but what's
going to be the ultimate fate of the
universe are we going to have a big
phrase are we going to have a big rip
are we going to have a big crunch big
freeze means eventually the universe
will keep expanding keep expanding keep
expanding and eventually all matter will
be so widely dispersed far apart from
each other that uh it will not be able
to interact with itself
and we will the universe will reach a
state of Maximum entropy disorder and
this is this is called the heat death of
the universe that's one possibility then
the Big Rip is mean is when Dark Energy
becomes so aggressive that not only are
planets
ripped out of their orbits from the
stars the moon will be ripped out of the
orbit of the Earth but so but atoms will
be ripped apart molecules will be ripped
about subatomic particles will be ripped
apart even the fabric of space-time
itself will be ripped apart that is the
Big Rip the Big Crunch means eventually
expansion stops and the universe starts
Contracting eventually it collapses upon
itself and becomes a new Singularity and
maybe a new Big Bang happens so these
are the possibilities that exist but we
don't know what's actually going to
happen there are so many open problems
and physics what is the dimensionality
of the universe how many dimensions does
the universe have we see the world in
three dimensions and we experience
something called time so those are four
dimensions that are involved in general
relativity four dimensional space-time
collusa Klein theory is about five
dimensions in the universe uh super
String Theory says there are it requires
10 Dimensions M Theory describes space
time as having 11 Dimensions bosonic
String Theory says there are 26
dimensions
has come up with a new Theory which says
that the Universe has e Dimensions e is
called Euler's number is equal to 2.71
A3 blah blah
it's it's it's an irrational number so
the universe may not be three
dimensional or four dimensional it may
be e dimensional it may be 2.7183
dimensional which is a mind-bending
prospect but the theory does seem to
make a lot of sense and it throws new
light on the origin of gravity and the
open problems of Dark Matter dark energy
and even the Hubble tension so there are
so many open problems in physics we know
next to nothing of the universe and we
are talking string theory
we keep on doing String Theory which
produces no results so that is why there
is this stagnation in theoretical
physics because the string theory Mafia
has taken over all the funding and all
the control in physics and there is this
this this uh permeate permeating group
think all over the place
and in the experimental physics it's the
it's the particle accelerators where all
the funding goes so all the funding goes
where well no new results are coming out
the Large Hadron Collider
is the most experiment the most
expensive scientific instrument ever
built it's produced one result
it's it's proven Peter Higgs right a
prediction he made in the 1950s or 1960s
the Higgs boson has been discovered
apart from that it has discovered
nothing new no supersymmetry no micro
black holes nothing
so we are dumping money we are pouring
money into the wrong Avenues
we need to look at different ways of
thinking
but we are doing group think so physics
needs to move away from string theory
and explore weird strange unexplored
domains ways of thinking let people
think differently let them come up with
ridiculous theories but at least
something new will come out of it so
that is the problem and that's why
theoretical physics is stagnating it
really makes me very angry anyhow I hope
that answers the question
VIP says what is more important in a war
a symbolic Victory or a strategic
Victory as in Ukraine Russia conflict
many are saying that the city of Bahamut
does not have much of a strategic
significance but they are still fighting
first let's put something on the screen
since we are talking about
they've been saying this for months that
Bahamut has no strategic significance
why are the Russians fighting so much
now what are they saying look here
exclusive this is from March 7. today is
March 12th so this week itself
this is from CNN zelinski Wars warns of
Open Road through Ukraine's East if
Russia captures bhagmud as he resists
call to retreat so for the longest time
they were saying the Russians are stupid
and they are fighting in this place
which has no strategic importance but
now zelinski himself is saying that
bhakmud is the key to Ukraine
they will have an open road through
Ukraine's East so please my dear friends
please don't trust the media the media
is misinformation the media is
propaganda the media wants to mislead
you the media is lying to you
all right so please understand that
so bhagmud is strategically vital and
that's why the ukrainians are throwing
so many unfortunate hapless soldiers
into the Bahamut meat grinder and yeah
we know what's happening the Russians
are on the verge of taking the city now
uh so what's important in the war
important in a war a strategic Victory
or or a symbolic Victory it's always a
strategic Victory that's important in a
war why do we fight Wars
a war has a certain objective a certain
political or geopolitical objective
so a war is fought to
to in in the pursuit of that objective
it's not pursued for symbolism or
whatever
you either want to capture a certain
amount of territory either otherwise you
want to capture the capital city and
affect the regime change
you may want to demilitarize a country
you may want to denotify a country these
are strategic objectives these are
geopolitical or political objectives
that's why you fight Wars
so if you fight a battle and you do a
heroic job but you don't achieve your
political objective then it's a it's a
loss
even if you win that battle
so what's the only thing thing that is
important in a war is to achieve your
the objectives which you had in mind
when you started the war you don't start
a war out of emotions or anger or
because you're furious with something
somebody said you start a war for very
clear objectives and that's the only
thing that's important in a war
rodrigit says in a federal democracy
like India various Regional parties are
using federalism to promote
sub-nationalism for their political
interests yes which is gradually
dividing India internally yes the effect
of this is clearly visible in South
Indian States if it continues like this
our country's Integrity won't just be
threatened from the outside but from
inside as well what is the solution
why is the situation the way it is today
why do local party local political
parties have so much power that they can
even indulge in soft secessionism soft
separatism
because
how are they able to do this it's
because of the Indian constitution
it's because of the way India has been
created the Constitution
it defines India as a union of states or
I don't know what exactly it is like but
the Constitution is the key to all this
unfortunately there is too much
democracy in India which means that the
regional parties and the regional the
states have too much power I'm not
saying they should not be empowered they
should have full Freedom economically
and and with respect to local policies
but when it comes to the National
interest only the center should be all
powerful so when it comes to
International Affairs when it comes to
diplomacy when it comes to military
Affairs and it went and when it comes to
uh when it comes to the National
interest the center should be Paramount
and there are certain red lines that
nobody should be allowed to cross under
no under any circumstances whatsoever
so for a nation to remain strong and
unified certain things cannot be allowed
to happen like sub-nationalism and and
and
soft separatism
and you know attacks on various
languages and and people from other
parts of the nation this should never
ever be allowed but in the current
scenario in the current
um system that we have it's it's par for
the course
so what India needs is a new
constitution
it's not that easy as it sounds I'm
making a new constitution because there
is no provision within this Constitution
that allows this constitution to be uh
discarded in a new constitution to be
brought in place so something will have
to be done eventually by and we will
need a really strong leader to to do
this the current constitution is nothing
but a mishmash of Western constitutions
there is nothing Indian about it
nothing in and about it whatsoever
so this constitution eventually has to
go and this is what uh Professor Gotham
desiraju also has spoken about in detail
in his conversation with me he's written
a book about this
that India needs a new Constitution or a
constitution that is rooted in Indian
values and Indian culture it should be
Indian and Indian civilization so the
current Constitution we have is a
western Constitution there is nothing
Indian about it and it is it is creating
all kinds of problems in India
so that is the solution
okay what next
says in our 10th standard history book
it's written that Mr Gandhi mentioned in
his book Hindi swaraj that if Indians
refuse to cooperate with the British
then we would have gotten Independence
in a matter of time but during the Royal
Indian Navy Mutiny incident the Navy
mutinid against the British but why did
Mr Gandhi send Mr Patel to negotiate
with the Navy and to suppress the Mutiny
doesn't that contradict what Gandhi said
before can we also say that Gandhi was
sold to the British later in the
independence struggle
uh so I don't know what is written in
that book henceforage I have not read a
Mr Gandhi's book well yeah because I was
not so inclined it's uh yeah
not interested so I haven't read his
book I don't know what is written in
that Mr Gandhi what we do know is the
events of the Indian the the British
Indian Navy's Rebellion which happened
in 1946 they all rebelled the entire
Indian Navy with the exception of one or
two ships rebelled against the British
and the Navy was stationed from all the
way from the Gulf of uh the Strait of
Hormuz in the Persian Gulf all the way
to this Strait of
what is it called the other straight
Malacca
all over there even Singapore
so we have this enormous Indian Navy and
everybody all the ships revolted against
the British it was a major disaster for
the British and if the Indian British
Indian army had come to know about this
and if they had rebelled it was the end
of British rule in India overnight like
that
so what Mr Gandhi did is that he said I
do not approve of this nonsense I will
not approve of any Rebellion against the
British
we can only Rebel non-violently and
through words no actions please no
actions so he dispatched Mr Patel
Sardar Patel to Bombay it was then
called Bombay it's now Mumbai but at
that time it was called Bombay so he
dispatched Mr Patel to Bombay to
negotiate with the uh with the sailors
and to make them
uh end their Rebellion so Mr Patel came
to Bombay he entered into negotiations
with with the representatives of the
Indian uh Indian Navy he told them Mr
Gandhi disapproves of this Mr Jinnah
also disapprove of that by the way
so Mr Gandhi disapprove of this and he
told them that listen you need to stop
this and I give you the assurance that
no action will be taken against you no
action will be taken against you just
lay down your arms and surrender
so because no political support was
forthcoming except for the Communist
party which has its own agenda the
Muslim League did not support the Mutiny
because they wanted their Pakistan and
Mutiny would be disastrous for that and
Mr Gandhi did not support it so the
Indian congress party did not did not
support so because of this the soldiers
they they lost their morale and they
surrendered and the moment they
surrendered they were arrested and
they were uh placed under Court martial
so Mr Patel whatever Assurance is he
gave those were empty words
uh
and they were immediately arrested and
prosecuted
so Mr Patel was
was Mr Gandhi's right hand man
he was a loyal servant and disciple of
Mr Gandhi whatever Mr Gandhi said Mr
Patel would carry it out
and Mr Patel was the was the was Mr
Gandhi's means of controlling the
congress party
so
Mr Gandhi opposed the Mutiny because if
the Mutiny the the Rebellion had
succeeded and the Indian army which was
stationed across the subcontinent had
come to know about this and they had
also rebelled that was the end of
British power overnight
the British ruled India through the
Armed Forces
political power flows out of the barrel
of a gun
they did not rule India because they are
the cooperation of various things or
whatever they ruled India through might
and force only
and when that instrument of rule turned
against them it would be the end of the
story in immediately overnight and Mr
Gandhi somehow did not want this
because then there would have been no
partition
and then maybe the Armed Forces
leadership would have taken taken over
and maybe they would have invited Mr
Bose back to India and then Mr Gandhi
would have been sidelined his party
would have been sidelined with the
Jinnah would have been sidelined and Mr
boes most likely who the Army held in a
very high regard Mr moose would have
been the leader of India quite possibly
so
for the sake of power for the sake of
politics or whatever you want to
interpret it interpret as Mr Gandhi
ensured that the the Rebellion ended and
India did not get its independence in
1946 itself
if this had succeeded India would have
gained independence through strength
through force not through negotiations
and politics and in 47 what happened is
that the British gave India so-called
Independence on a platter it was a
transfer of power from one set of crooks
to another set of crooks
and as a result India is still
bearing the consequences of all that
even today
so that's the story that's what really
happened can we say that Mr Gandhi was
sold to the British later in the
independent Circle later earlier if at
all if not I will leave that to you to
decide and to conclude you are
intelligent enough to understand what
really happened
Sarang says I was surprised to find that
many of my friends don't think that
preserving Indian culture is important
why do you think this is the case is it
because of the education system is it
because of the western-led media what
can we as citizens of India do to make
our country's relationship with English
and our own languages similar to that of
French and English and France their
education and everything is in French
but they are not too bad at English
listen the French don't really like to
speak English they prefer French okay so
why is it so listen if you don't teach
anything about your culture
in school then the kids will have no
connection with their culture and then
they will feel there's no what's the
point there's no harm in in getting rid
of Indian culture
the Indian education system does not
teach Indian culture at all
to the students there is no connection
so when there's no connection there's no
value that's why your friends don't
think that preserving Indian culture is
important because they don't even know
what Indian culture is they don't feel
any sense of belonging any sense of
connection
any sense of value that's the reason the
education system is designed to destroy
Indian culture
that's what it's designed to do
it's the it's the continuation of the
19th century colonial education system
yesterday they will teach you computer
science and they will give you MBA
degrees and all that but it's the same
education system the same format
the same purpose it's not designed to
teach you how to think it's designed to
tell you what to think it's not designed
to turn out leaders it's designed to
turn out sheep
so mainly it's because of the education
system see the Chinese have their own
education system they are also exposed
to Western media when Western media when
they come out of China but they don't
become anti-china they don't uh you know
turn their back on Chinese culture it's
because the education system is right
for them
I don't know what they teach but I'm
sure that they teach Chinese culture and
and they inculcate a sense of pride in
the culture and and patriotism and all
those things India doesn't do that at
all
the Indian education teacher if the
system teaches kids to hate their own
culture and their own ancestors
that's the deal
so that's the reason why your friends
don't think it's important to preserve
Indian culture they think Indian culture
is inferior and bad and misogynistic and
patriarch and blah blah blah blah blah
all that you know
um what can we do to make our country's
relationship with English and our
language is similar listen everybody
should try and learn their own language
try and read some books in your own
language try and learn Sanskrit if you
can one of the things you could do is
purchase a copy of some book in Sanskrit
and in English or whatever language you
prefer
for instance
purchase a copy of the ramayan or the
bhagavad-gita in Sanskrit and purchase
the exact translation in whatever
language you prefer and then read both
you do this this process over a year or
so you will actually end up learning a
lot of Sanskrit so this is what you can
do or you can read books written in your
your own native language everybody
should have some connection with their
language
so so we cannot blame the keep blaming
the government for for everything
obviously they are not doing their job
of promoting Indian languages so let's
take the initiative of ourselves buy a
book in your own native language or
whatever language you're fond of
and read that
spend some time doing this some some
time doing that we need to all all take
the initiative that's what we can do as
people
as Citizens
Neil Mandel says please guide me how to
rebuild curiosity as it was in my
childhood currently I'm a teenager how
to regain the joint of learn the joy of
learning questioning reading books
understanding
Etc my curiosity is killed because of
the pressure from society and the
education system harsh teachers boring
useless books fear fearful exams
which says to memorize everything
instead of questioning
we have forgotten to we've forgotten to
question why now I hate books and my
mind has stopped observing and
questioning the surroundings such as
earlier I used to ask questions on
topics such as the universe technology
environment biology philosophy physics
languages but now I'm trying now I'm
trying but getting failure to regain my
curiosity as it was back then
listen you clearly understand that
something has happened and uh
because of the education system and all
that you don't like books anymore okay
we understand that we all go through
that uh what you really need see you
actually do understand and you do
realize something has happened so to
read to rebuild or rekindle the
Curiosity uh
you first of all need some time to
yourself if you're always surrounded by
people who all think the same way then
it's impossible to think differently you
need to have some some time alone to
yourself in a day maybe a couple of
hours and then try to go back to the
feeling of how it was when you were a
child and what things you are interested
in
so today teachers will tell you that
your question is stupid or whatever they
will not answer your question but today
you have the internet
so think about those things you used to
be curious about and fascinated with and
passionate about as a kid as a younger
kid and today you don't need teachers
just use Google or whatever it is all
the information is available on the
internet learn how to search the
internet
and and study whatever whatever makes
you curious
so
it's about you know
making some space for yourself finding
some time for yourself where your alone
time your private time in your privacy
you can pursue certain Pursuits you know
so uh and not all books are boring you
have to open an interesting book
so if you okay just surround yourself
with your school textbooks it's gonna
remain boring so it's it's when you when
there is a distance between you and
whatever you were curious about or
whatever you enjoyed there will be a
process of climbing up that hill again
so
so I would say find some book or if you
don't like books anymore use the
internet but you have to find a way of
of reconnecting with things that you are
passionate about
so um at the end of the day we all go
through the education system we all face
it
and that's not gonna be the excuse we
can use to you know not be curious
anymore you've got to preserve that that
the thing that was good inside you you
know you you have to fight for it so you
fight for it fight by finding time for
yourself let's say two hours a day then
you will not allow anyone to distract
you and then pursue your curiosity
rebuild it reignited it's definitely
possible
okay uh let's take some questions from
the live chat I have more questions uh
that I picked but let's take some
questions from the live chat maybe 10-15
minutes of that
so if you have any questions for me
then you can ask me now in the live chat
and I will try and
take some of these
Bobby says over time the Indian
education system could be worthless it
can happen but it will take some doing
there will be a lot of internal
resistance from the stakeholders those
who
those who benefit from the way the
Indian education system is and the
entire system is built that way so even
well-meaning people will think that the
education system the way it is is good
so there's going to be a huge amount of
internal resistance if any kind of
change or reform is attempted but yes uh
once if we have a strong enough
leadership then it can certainly happen
in overtime it can become world-class
okay other questions
um let's see what other questions we
have
um
Silicon Valley Bank collapse in the U.S
yes that svb the Silicon Valley Bank has
collapsed it's it's I think on the verge
of bankruptcy already bankrupt
and yeah it tells you what sort of
system they have until recently just a
month or so ago they were saying it was
one of the best banks in the in the
world in the US Forbes had given it some
some uh some recognition and all that
and just a few days later it collapses
so yeah maybe I should in a future
episode analyze what really happened
there but yeah that's what it is
um will Putin attend G20 meeting this
year in India
I doubt if you will attend it
see Mr Putin is more or less isolated by
the West
and
I think he would not like to travel
outside his country where he cannot
control everything there is definitely
when when you are the the president of
Russia and Russia is standing up to the
West there is definitely the possibility
and the chance of the leader of Russia
being assassinated somewhere
so it is it is something that Mr Putin
would not want to do he does travel to
the S to to to various neighboring
countries where he can control where his
where his government can control the
situation very well but uh
but yeah apart from that he right now is
not traveling much far from his Nation
so I think it is unlikely that Mr Putin
will attend the G20 Summit this year in
the in the end of this year in India I
think it's unlikely
okay uh
how to remember everything for upsc well
um I've never done that so I don't know
I I suppose you've got to find some um
see I'm not the right person to ask this
I have never tried to memorize
everything and remember everything
that's not what I do
so maybe you should join a coaching
class or something where they teach you
the techniques of how to memorize things
and all that I think
that's the best answer I can give you
I'm not big on memorizing things and
remembering everything especially
information that is not really useful
so everything for you what you study for
upsc much of it is really
not that useful in real life
how to control smartphone addiction find
something else to replace that find
something better to replace that
so smartphone addiction I suppose it's
where you keep scrolling through
Instagram or whatever right that's what
you do I I guess you have to
find something more interesting that you
can do
maybe go play sports when you're playing
sports football Cricket you can't have
this part smartphone with you yeah so
that's one thing you can do so a couple
of hours of that per day it will make
you healthier stronger and it will keep
the smartphone away or maybe if you are
so inclined
pick up reading pick up wrestling pick
up weightlifting or go on a run go on a
walk I don't know you've got to find
something else to replace it that's the
main thing you want to do
um
okay let's see this recent research
paper indicates the extinction of
dinosaurs to Deccan flood basalts rather
than the chocolate impact there is no
Chrono stratigraphic evidence of this
well I haven't seen this I haven't seen
this this is the first time I'm hearing
of this
so uh Deccan flood basalts rather than
the Joker of impact see
the extinction of the dinosaurs happened
roughly 66
million years ago
and at that time there were two things
two big things happening on our planet
one is the loop impact which could have
been a multiple impact not just one but
multiple impacts maybe the the impactor
the store The Rock broke up
and there were multiple impacts that is
a possibility there is this big Crater
of the west coast of India it's called
the Shiva crater which also seems to
date back to about 66 million years ago
so it could have could have been a
multiple impact event apart from that
there was another major event happening
in the world which was the Deccan traps
volcanism
so if you look at the central India
Deccan region you can see evidence of
extinct volcanic activity the Deccan
traps the Badlands of India the
Hinterlands of India so there was this
big super volcano eruption going on at
the time at that time the Indian
subcontinent was not part of it was not
attached to Eurasia at that time it was
it was somewhere in the Indian Ocean
over the reunion hotspot which is where
the volcanism happened so it is possible
that it was not just the impact event
but also this massive volcanism and all
the gas and everything that came out of
it that could have together
these two things together could have
contributed to the extinction event that
killed off the non-avian dinosaurs so
when you have a super volcanic volcanic
eruption happening
a subcontinent-sized volcanic activity
happening you will have those the
extinction of dinosaurs in India because
of that itself you would not need an
impact event half the world away for the
dinosaurs to die off
so um there's been a big battle going
for the longest time as to what killed
of the dinosaurs was it the check Club
impact event or was it the Deccan traps
volcanism most likely it was a
combination of both factors but when it
comes to the dinosaurs within India
itself who lived in India they would
have been affected primarily by the
Deccan traps volcanism and uh
so yeah so it's an interesting uh piece
of news that you are referencing over
here and I will definitely look that up
so these are my preliminary thoughts
about what you are offering here
interesting very interesting
okay let's see what else do we have any
other interesting questions
um
okay this how many planets are there in
the solar system well it depends on what
you call Pluto some people say Pluto is
no longer a planet it is a minor planet
or a dwarf planet or whatever they said
I don't care for me Pluto is a planet
when I when I was a kid I thought of
Pluto as a parent and I will always
think of Pluto as a planet obviously
it's very small it's it's comparable in
size to Earth's moon
so uh
how many let's let's assume that we will
call Pluto or planet planet in that case
we have nine confirmed planets in the
solar system obviously Beyond planet in
the Caper belt and all that we will have
other objects which are lurking around
they have discovered lots of minor
planets or planetoids or planetesimals
such as sedna and kawawar and makeemake
and haumea and whatever the names
they've given
minor planets smaller than Pluto there
is Iris which is bigger than Pluto
larger than Pluto and there could be
much more lurking out there in the deep
deep far-off reaches of the solar system
the solar system it stretches outwards
more than a light year away from the Sun
uh there's the Wood Cloud which is this
which is hypothetical huge cloud of icy
objects which which is which is our
plants which is where comets come from
and there is the possibility that there
could be a hidden Planet somewhere out
there because when we look at the Caper
belt objects and other objects over
there there
their orbits are inclined weirdly which
is something that would happen when
there is an unknown massive object
lurking out there so there could be a
large Rocky or maybe non-rocky Planet
out there but it's not thus far been
detected it's so it may be so far from
the Sun that it may not be visible or
really very well visible in sunlight so
we know of nine at least but there could
be more out there
space is enormous it's vast and who
knows what else is lurking out there in
the far reaches of the solar system
let's take one more question
um
is it true that Mr Gandhi wanted to
dissolve the Congress yeah I believe
that he said that uh once Independence
is achieved the Congress is no longer
required and the Congress should be
dissolved but obviously they did not
agree with that and the Congress still
exists
uh lots of the questions
um
Ajay ready says what can the rapid
Dragon missile launching system be used
for our missiles and is it effective
can it be integrated with high altitude
balloons I am not aware of this rapid
Dragon missile launching system haven't
heard of it so I will look it up and
maybe I can answer this next time
interesting question
is the younger dryas event mentioned in
any Indian scriptures there are mentions
of floods in Indian scriptures if there
was an impact event like the
hypothetical Young address event may be
real then there could have been flooding
in various parts of the world including
in the Indian subcontinent so there is
this this story of the flood the Manus
flood or whatever it is so that could
perhaps reference an ancient flood which
could have been triggered off by the
younger impact event so possibly perhaps
but we don't have clear
uh evidence of that unequivocal evidence
of that
AK the guy says is the USA systematic or
institutional dictatorship see first of
all understand
it's come out in the news right that the
Pentagon has blocked Joe Biden's
Administration from going to the
international court of justice and and
complain about Russia so it tells you
that the Pentagon which is the Deep
State the military establishment of the
US is more powerful than the White House
than the elected government of the U.S
so the relationship between the Pentagon
and the White House is the same as the
relationship between rawal Pindi and
Islamabad Rahal Pindi is way more
powerful than Islamabad similar to The
Pentagon it's way more powerful than the
White House then the democratically
elected government of the U.S the
Pentagon is unelected
um
and the US is a two-party state which is
just one step above a one-party system
like the Chinese Communist party or
North Korea just one step above that
two-party system so the US is not really
a
democracy please understand that you
could think of it as as a nation that's
run by a hidden bunch of people that's
what the US is
all right
is democracy Sham in like any system we
would expect democracy to evolve in
India but it seems neither government or
people seem to be working on it see we
need to have a better Constitution a
better system and then democracy will
really work India is the birthplace of
democracy but we had our own system of
democracy
so democracy
at the very top you had Emperors and
Kings but at the Grassroots level you
had democracy people would elect their
own officials who would then work for
the people it was a hybrid kind of
system but it was way more democratic
than whatever emerged out of Greece much
later
so democracy in today's world is
definitely a sham look at the U.S
and even in a properly Democratic
country when you can rig the system by
by indulging in in vote Bank politics
and all that defeats the purpose of
democracy
when you can do vote Bank politics it
totally defeats the purpose of democracy
so overall democracy is more or less a
sham and if you have too much democracy
it's actually harmful to your nation
so that's what I can say let's not blame
the Indian people for this we have this
tendency of self-flagellation
keep blaming ourselves
it is not the fault of the Indian people
that the country is in the situation it
is not the fault of the Indian people
that power was handed from one set of
crooks to another set of crooks in 1947.
it is not the Indian people's fault that
this Constitution which says we the
people was imposed undemocratically on
India without it ever being ratified by
the people of India
understand what really has happened stop
blaming ourselves but that's what we
need to do and with that I'm gonna end
today's session
with that I'm gonna and let's take one
more
why is Pok now crying for help after 75
years also there is news of a demand for
Indonesian Pakistan since they've been
asking for it for it for a very long
time Pok is now crying for help and they
are saying that Pakistan has given us
nothing for the longest time they
supported Pakistan
for the longest time they supported
Pakistan when the pakistanis the the
Raiders the tribals created
did Untold atrocities massacres
in in Kashmir in 1948 despite that the
people of Pok supported Pakistan but now
they can see that Pakistan is a is a
failed State and India has progressed
Way Beyond anything Pakistan can ever
achieve and
and Kashmir is doing so well now
right so po the people of PUK are
feeling left out so now they are crying
for help
all right because they want a better
deal they want a better quality of life
they want better standards of Life they
want better education everything is
available across the border in India in
Kashmir but in Pok there's nothing they
are marginalized they are treated like
step children that is the deal so that's
why they're crying for help
but they always supported Pakistan for
the longest time
anyway we will eventually reintegrate
poke with India sooner rather than later
Pakistan is a temporary Nation as you
know it's going to happen soon maybe
very soon let's see
all right with that we end today's
session thank you very much everybody
for the wonderful questions it's always
fun taking these questions and answering
them all and
um we will I'll see you all very soon in
the next live stream until then take
care
and
good night good day wherever you are see
you soon bye